The Great Soul Trial Collection, 1962-1981 (bulk 1966-1974)
University of Arizona Libraries, Special Collections
The Great Soul Trial Collection, 1962-1981 (bulk 1966-1974)
MS 542
Myers, Robert
The Great Soul Trial was first held in Phoenix, Arizona in 1967 and went to retrial in 1971. The purpose of the trial was to honor the will of James Kidd that left money to fund scientific research that provided proof of a human soul that leaves the body at the time of death. The collection contains correspondence, claimant materials, press clippings, photographs, audio recordings, and oversize materials.
16 linear feet
University of Arizona Libraries, Special Collections University of Arizona PO Box 210055 Tucson, AZ 85721-0055 Phone: 520-621-6423 Fax: 520-621-9733 URL: http://speccoll.library.arizona.edu/ E-Mail: LBRY-askspcoll@email.arizona.edu
Restrictions
There are no restrictions on this collection.
Historical Note
James Kidd was born on July 18, 1879 in Ogdensburgh, New York. He held residence on the outskirts of Phoenix, Arizona and was an employee of the Miami Company of Arizona. In November, 1949 Kidd went missing in the Superstition Mountains outside of Phoenix, Arizona. In 1954, he was declared missing and dead by the State of Arizona. In 1964, the State of Arizona took an inventory of a safety deposit box owned by James Kidd which contained a holograph will dating from 1930 stating his wishes that the balance of his estate go towards funding research that provided scientific proof of the existence of a soul that leaves the human body at the time of death. The value of the estate after expenses was in excess of $200,000. The estate went to trial between May – October, 1967 as James Kidd had no heirs or immediate family. The Honorable Justice Robert Myers of the Court of Maricopa County, Arizona presided over the case and heard from one hundred thirty three claimants over the course of the hearings. On October 20, 1967 the estate was awarded to the Barrow Neurological Institute located in Phoenix, Arizona. In 1971, The Arizona Supreme Court overturned the decision handed down by Justice Robert Myers, which resulted in the case going to retrial that year. Again, Justice Robert Myers presided over the case and awarded the estate to the American Society for Psychical Research based in New York City, New York.
Arrangement
This collection is organized into six series.
Series I: Correspondence, 1966-1979
Series II: Claimant Materials, 1966-1981
Series III: Press Clippings, 1966-1971
Series IV: Photographs, 1967
Series V: Publications, 1962-1970
Series VI: Audio Recordings, 1966-1967
Scope and Content Note
This collection contains correspondence, claimant materials, press clippings, photographs, publications, and oversize materials collected by Justice Robert Myers who presided over The Great Soul Trial in 1967 and when the case went to retrial in 1971. The correspondence series comprises the bulk of the collection and is arranged alphabetically by country. The bulk of the correspondence is from the United States and is arranged alphabetically. This series consists of correspondence, essays, monographs, photographs, artwork, diagrams, etc. sent by individuals and organizations applying for claim on the James Kidd estate. The Claimant Materials series contains correspondence from applicants that were selected to testify for claim on the James Kidd estate by the Court of Maricopa County, Arizona. This series also contains final accounting and petition for final distribution materials and a list of claimants and petitioners. The Press Clippings series contains newspaper clippings and magazine articles from publications based worldwide documenting the Great Soul Trial and its proceedings. The photographs series contains photographs of Justice Robert Myers and various claimants that testified during the Great Soul Trial. The publications series contains monographs and pamphlets that were sent by individuals applying for claim on the James Kidd estate. The audio recordings series contains reel to reel tapes sent by individuals applying for claim on the James Kidd estate.
For more information, see the monograph The Great Soul Trial by John G. Fuller.
Access Terms
Metaphysical research.
Metaphysics.
Spirituality.
Spiritual life--Christianity.
Spiritual life--Hinduism.
Spiritual life--Judaism.
Spiritual life--Buddhism.
Spiritual life--Islam.
Correspondence—1960-1970.
Courts—United States—Cases.
Law—United States—Cases.
Religion and law—United States--Cases.
Container List
- Series 1: Correspondence, 1966-1979
  This series contains correspondence and is arranged alphabetically by country. The bulk of the materials originates from the United States which is arranged alphabetically. The miscellaneous folders located towards the end of the series contains materials from Bolivia, Spain, Nicaragua, Guatemala, Sri Lanka, New Caledonia, Pakistan, Leeward Islands, Mauritius, Panama, Uruguay, Netherlands, Mozambique, Poland, Taiwan, Lebanon, Kenya, New Zealand, Israel, China, Puerto Rico, CCCP, Holland, Poland, Portugal, Iran, South Korea, Japan, Manila, Ghana, Togo, Liberia, and Indonesia. Anonymous folders located at the end of the series contain correspondence from unidentified individuals. Box 14 contains oversize materials and consists of correspondence from claimant applicants, a record album, and a list of correspondence arranged by country created by office of Justice Robert Myers.
  Materials within this series consists of correspondence, essays, monographs, photographs, artwork, diagrams, etc. sent by individuals and organizations applying for claim on the James Kidd estate. The materials discuss a myriad of spiritual beliefs and practices, including but not limited to Christianity, Hinduism, Buddhist, Islam, and Shintoism. Materials are in English, German, Spanish, Portuguese, Tamil, Hindi, Japanese, French, Urdu, Dutch, Polish, Mandarin, Arabic, Swahili, Hebrew, Russian, Persian, Korean, Tagalog, and Indonesian.
  - Argentina, 1966-1968 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Australia, 1967 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Austria (1 of 2), 1966-1974 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Austria (2 of 2), 1966-1974 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Austria (2 of 2), 1966-1974 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Belgium, 1966-1969 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Bolivia, 1966-1969 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Brazil (1 of 3), 1966-1972 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Brazil (2 of 3), 1966-1972 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Brazil (3 of 3), 1966-1972 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Canada (1 of 3), 1966-1968 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Canada (2 of 3), 1966-1968 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Canada (3 of 3), 1966-1968 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Canada, 1971-1974 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Chile, 1966-1967 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Columbia (1 of 2), 1966-1969 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Columbia (2 of 2), 1966-1969 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Costa Rica, 1966-1967 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Czechoslovakia, 1966-1967 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Denmark, 1966-1967 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Ecuador, 1966-1967 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - France (1 of 2), 1966-1967 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - France (2 of 2), 1966-1967 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Germany (1 of 10), 1966-1968 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Germany (2 of 10), 1966-1968 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Germany (3 of 10), 1966-1968 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Germany (4 of 10), 1966-1968 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Germany (5 of 10), 1966-1968 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Germany (6 of 10), 1966-1968 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Germany (7 of 10), 1966-1968 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Germany (8 of 10), 1966-1968 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Germany (9 of 10), 1966-1968 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Germany (10 of 10), 1966-1968 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Germany, 1970-1971 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Greece, 1967-1968 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Hungary, 1966-1969 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - India (1 of 29), 1966-1968 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - India (2 of 29), 1966-1968 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - India (3 of 29), 1966-1968 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - India (4 of 29), 1966-1968 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - India (5 of 29), 1966-1968 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - India (6 of 29), 1966-1968 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - India (7 of 29), 1966-1968 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - India (8 of 29), 1966-1968 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - India (9 of 29), 1966-1968 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - India (10 of 29), 1966-1968 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - India (11 of 29), 1966-1968 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - India (12 of 29), 1966-1968 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - India (13 of 29), 1966-1968 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - India (14 of 29), 1966-1968 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - India (15 of 29), 1966-1968 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - India (16 of 29), 1966-1968 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - India (17 of 29), 1966-1968 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - India (18 of 29), 1966-1968 (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - India (19 of 29), 1966-1968 (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - India (20 of 29), 1966-1968 (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - India (21 of 29), 1966-1968 (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - India (22 of 29), 1966-1968 (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - India (23 of 29), 1966-1968 (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - India (24 of 29), 1966-1968 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - India (25 of 29), 1966-1968 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - India (26 of 29), 1966-1968 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - India (27 of 29), 1966-1968 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - India (28 of 29), 1966-1968 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - India (29 of 29), 1966-1968 (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - India, 1969-1971 (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Italy (1 of 3), 1966-1967 (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Italy (2 of 3), 1966-1967 (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - Italy (3 of 3), 1966-1967 (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - Mexico, 1966-1967 (Box 5, Folder 11)
  - Mexico, 1968-1970 (Box 5, Folder 12)
  - Norway, 1966-1967 (Box 5, Folder 13)
  - Peru, 1966-1967 (Box 5, Folder 14)
  - Philippines, 1967-1968 (Box 5, Folder 15)
  - South Africa, 1966-1968 (Box 5, Folder 16)
  - Sweden, 1966-1969 (Box 5, Folder 17)
  - Switzerland, 1966-1967 (Box 5, Folder 18)
  - Turkey, 1966-1968 (Box 5, Folder 19)
  - United Kingdom (1 of 3), 1966-1968 (Box 5, Folder 20)
  - United Kingdom (2 of 3), 1966-1968 (Box 5, Folder 21)
  - United Kingdom (3 of 3), 1966-1968 (Box 5, Folder 22)
  - United Kingdom, 1970 (Box 5, Folder 23)
  - United States; A (1 of 3), 1966-1967 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - United States; A (2 of 3), 1966-1967 (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - United States; A (3 of 3), 1966-1967 (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - United States; A, 1969-1971 (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - United States; B (1 of 6), 1966-1968 (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - United States; B (2 of 6), 1966-1968 (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - United States; B (3 of 6), 1966-1968 (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - United States; B (4 of 6), 1966-1968 (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - United States; B (5 of 6), 1966-1968 (Box 6, Folder 9)
  - United States; B (6 of 6), 1966-1968 (Box 6, Folder 10)
  - United States; B, 1969-1975 (Box 6, Folder 11)
  - United States; C (1 of 10), 1966-1968 (Box 6, Folder 12)
  - United States; C (2 of 10), 1966-1968 (Box 6, Folder 13)
  - United States; C (3 of 10), 1966-1968 (Box 6, Folder 14)
  - United States; C (4 of 10), 1966-1968 (Box 6, Folder 15)
  - United States; C (5 of 10), 1966-1968 (Box 6, Folder 16)
  - United States; C (6 of 10), 1966-1968 (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - United States; C (7 of 10), 1966-1968 (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - United States; C (8 of 10), 1966-1968 (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - United States; C (9 of 10), 1966-1968 (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - United States; C (10 of 10), 1966-1968 (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - United States; C (1 of 2), 1969-1976 (Box 7, Folder 6)
  - United States; C (2 of 2), 1969-1976 (Box 7, Folder 7)
  - United States; D (1 of 3), 1966-1968 (Box 7, Folder 8)
  - United States; D (2 of 3), 1966-1968 (Box 7, Folder 9)
  - United States; D (3 of 3), 1966-1968 (Box 7, Folder 10)
  - United States; D, 1969-1971 (Box 7, Folder 11)
  - United States; E (1 of 2), 1966-1968 (Box 7, Folder 12)
  - United States; E (2 of 2), 1966-1968 (Box 7, Folder 13)
  - United States; E, 1970-1971 (Box 7, Folder 14)
  - United States; F (1 of 4), 1966-1968 (Box 7, Folder 15)
  - United States; F (2 of 4), 1966-1968 (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - United States; F (3 of 4), 1966-1968 (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - United States; F (4 of 4), 1966-1968 (Box 8, Folder 3)
  - United States; F, 1969-1971 (Box 8, Folder 4)
  - United States; G (1 of 4), 1966-1968 (Box 8, Folder 5)
  - United States; G (2 of 4), 1966-1968 (Box 8, Folder 6)
  - United States; G (3 of 4), 1966-1968 (Box 8, Folder 7)
  - United States; G (4 of 4), 1966-1968 (Box 8, Folder 8)
  - United States; G, 1971-1973 (Box 8, Folder 9)
  - United States; H (1 of 5), 1966-1968 (Box 8, Folder 10)
  - United States; H (2 of 5), 1966-1968 (Box 8, Folder 11)
  - United States; H (3 of 5), 1966-1968 (Box 8, Folder 12)
  - United States; H (4 of 5), 1966-1968 (Box 8, Folder 13)
  - United States; H (5 of 5), 1966-1968 (Box 8, Folder 14)
  - United States; H, 1969-1973 (Box 8, Folder 15)
  - United States; I, 1966-1967 (Box 8, Folder 16)
  - United States; J (1 of 3), 1966-1968 (Box 8, Folder 17)
  - United States; J (2 of 3), 1966-1968 (Box 9, Folder 1)
  - United States; J (3 of 3), 1966-1968 (Box 9, Folder 2)
  - United States; J, 1971-1974 (Box 9, Folder 3)
  - United States; K (1 of 4), 1966-1968 (Box 9, Folder 4)
  - United States; K (2 of 4), 1966-1968 (Box 9, Folder 5)
  - United States; K (3 of 4), 1966-1968 (Box 9, Folder 6)
  - United States; K (4 of 4), 1966-1968 (Box 9, Folder 7)
  - United States; K, 1969-1972 (Box 9, Folder 8)
  - United States; L (1 of 4), 1966-1968 (Box 9, Folder 9)
  - United States; L (2 of 4), 1966-1968 (Box 9, Folder 10)
  - United States; L (3 of 4), 1966-1968 (Box 9, Folder 11)
  - United States; L (4 of 4), 1966-1968 (Box 9, Folder 12)
  - United States; L, 1971 (Box 9, Folder 13)
  - United States; M (1 of 9), 1966-1968 (Box 9, Folder 14)
  - United States; M (2 of 9), 1966-1968 (Box 9, Folder 15)
  - United States; M (3 of 9), 1966-1968 (Box 10, Folder 1)
  - United States; M (4 of 9), 1966-1968 (Box 10, Folder 2)
  - United States; M (5 of 9), 1966-1968 (Box 10, Folder 3)
  - United States; M (6 of 9), 1966-1968 (Box 10, Folder 4)
  - United States; M (7 of 9), 1966-1968 (Box 10, Folder 5)
  - United States; M (8 of 9), 1966-1968 (Box 10, Folder 6)
  - United States; M (9 of 9), 1966-1968 (Box 10, Folder 7)
  - United States; M, 1969-1971 (Box 10, Folder 8)
  - United States; N, 1968-1968 (Box 10, Folder 9)
  - United States; N, 1971 (Box 10, Folder 10)
  - United States; O, 1966-1967 (Box 10, Folder 11)
  - United States; O, 1969-1971 (Box 10, Folder 12)
  - United States; P (1 of 3), 1966-1968 (Box 10, Folder 13)
  - United States; P (2 of 3), 1966-1968 (Box 10, Folder 14)
  - United States; P (3 of 3), 1966-1968 (Box 10, Folder 15)
  - United States; P, 1970-1972 (Box 10, Folder 16)
  - United States; Q, 1966-1967 (Box 10, Folder 17)
  - United States; R (1 of 7), 1966-1968 (Box 11, Folder 1)
  - United States; R (2 of 7), 1966-1968 (Box 11, Folder 2)
  - United States; R (3 of 7), 1966-1968 (Box 11, Folder 3)
  - United States; R (4 of 7), 1966-1968 (Box 11, Folder 4)
  - United States; R (5 of 7), 1966-1968 (Box 11, Folder 5)
  - United States; R (6 of 7), 1966-1968 (Box 11, Folder 6)
  - United States; R (7 of 7), 1966-1968 (Box 11, Folder 7)
  - United States; R (1 of 2), 1969-1972 (Box 11, Folder 8)
  - United States; R (2 of 2), 1969-1972 (Box 11, Folder 9)
  - United States; S (1 of 10), 1966-1968 (Box 11, Folder 10)
  - United States; S (2 of 10), 1966-1968 (Box 11, Folder 11)
  - United States; S (3 of 10), 1966-1968 (Box 11, Folder 12)
  - United States; S (4 of 10), 1966-1968 (Box 11, Folder 13)
  - United States; S (5 of 10), 1966-1968 (Box 11, Folder 14)
  - United States; S (6 of 10), 1966-1968 (Box 12, Folder 1)
  - United States; S (7 of 10), 1966-1968 (Box 12, Folder 2)
  - United States; S (8 of 10), 1966-1968 (Box 12, Folder 3)
  - United States; S (9 of 10), 1966-1968 (Box 12, Folder 4)
  - United States; S (10 of 10), 1966-1968 (Box 12, Folder 5)
  - United States; S (1 of 2), 1969-1972 (Box 12, Folder 6)
  - United States; S (2 of 2), 1969-1972 (Box 12, Folder 7)
  - United States; T (1 of 3), 1966-1968 (Box 12, Folder 8)
  - United States; T (2 of 3), 1966-1968 (Box 12, Folder 9)
  - United States; T (3 of 3), 1966-1968 (Box 12, Folder 10)
  - United States; T, 1969-1978 (Box 12, Folder 11)
  - United States; U, 1967-1971 (Box 12, Folder 12)
  - United States; V, 1966-1967 (Box 12, Folder 13)
  - United States; V, 1970-1971 (Box 12, Folder 14)
  - United States; W (1 of 7), 1966-1968 (Box 12, Folder 15)
  - United States; W (2 of 7), 1966-1968 (Box 12, Folder 16)
  - United States; W (3 of 7), 1966-1968 (Box 12, Folder 17)
  - United States; W (4 of 7), 1966-1968 (Box 13, Folder 1)
  - United States; W (5 of 7), 1966-1968 (Box 13, Folder 2)
  - United States; W (6 of 7), 1966-1968 (Box 13, Folder 3)
  - United States; W (7 of 7), 1966-1968 (Box 13, Folder 4)
  - United States; W, 1969-1975 (Box 13, Folder 5)
  - United States; X, Y, 1966-1971 (Box 13, Folder 6)
  - United States; Z, 1966-1971 (Box 13, Folder 7)
  - United States; Anonymous (1 of 2), 1966-1967 (Box 13, Folder 8)
  - United States; Anonymous (2 of 2), 1966-1967 (Box 13, Folder 9)
  - Venezuela, 1967-1969 (Box 13, Folder 10)
  - Vietnam, 1967 (Box 13, Folder 11)
  - Yugoslavia, 1966-1969 (Box 13, Folder 12)
  - Miscellaneous (1 of 2), 1966-1971 (Box 13, Folder 13)
  - Miscellaneous (2 of 2), 1966-1971 (Box 13, Folder 14)
  - Henry, Richard Eus Correspondence (1 of 3), 1967 (Box 14, Item 1)
  - Henry, Richard Eus Correspondence (2 of 3), 1967 (Box 14, Item 2)
  - Henry, Richard Eus Correspondence (3 of 3), 1967 (Box 14, Item 3)
  - Anonymous Correspondence on Wood Piece, undated (Box 14, Item 4)
  - Kittinger, Kenneth C., Ph.D., News: A Discovery of the Mind Record Album, undated (Box 14, Item 5)
  - McCullough, Forrest, Final Flight: A Dramatic Comparison to Death Record Album, 1965 (Box 14, Item 6)
  - Davis, Alvin W. Correspondence, undated (Box 14, Item 7)
  - List of Correspondence by Country, undated (Box 14, Item 7)
- Series 2: Claimant Materials, 1966-1981
  This series contains correspondence from applicants that were selected to testify for claim on the James Kidd estate by the Court of Maricopa County, Arizona. This series also contains final accounting and petition for final distribution materials and a List of claimants and petitioners that were created by the staff of Justice Robert Myers.
  - Correspondence (1 of 5), 1966-1979 (Box 15, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence (2 of 5), 1966-1979 (Box 15, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence (3 of 5), 1966-1979 (Box 15, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence (4 of 5), 1966-1979 (Box 15, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence (5 of 5), 1966-1979 (Box 15, Folder 5)
  - Final Accounting and Petition for Final Distribution, 1967-1981 (Box 15, Folder 6)
  - List of Claimants and Petitioners, 1967 (Box 15, Folder 7)
- Series 2: Press Clippings, 1966-1971
  This series contains newspaper clippings and magazine articles from publications based worldwide documenting the Great Soul Trial and its proceedings.
  - 1966-1971 (1 of 3) (Box 15, Folder 8)
  - 1966-1971 (2 of 3) (Box 15, Folder 9)
  - 1966-1971 (3 of 3) (Box 15, Folder 10)
- Series 4: Photographs, 1967
  This series contains photographs of Justice Robert Meyers, his staff, and various claimants that testified during the Great Soul Trial.
  - Photographs of Judge Myers, His Staff, and Various Claimants, 1967 (Box 15, Folder 11)
- Series 5: Publications, 1962-1970
  This series contains monographs and pamphlets that were sent by individuals applying for claim on the James Kidd estate.
  - Books, 1962-1970 (Box 15, Folder 12)
  - Books and Pamphlets, 1962-1970 (Box 15, Folder 13)
- Series 6: Audio Recordings, 1966-1967
  This series contains aural documents on reel to reel tapes sent by individuals applying for claim on the James Kidd estate.
  - Padd, Chief, 1967 (Box 16, Tape 1)
  - Lynn, Rev. Walter, 1967 (Box 16, Tape 2)
  - Thompson, G.E., 1967 (Box 16, Tape 3)
  - Walters, Edith G., 1966 (Box 16, Tape 4)
  - Collier, W.W., 1967 (Box 16, Tape 5)